The human adventure is just beginning.
Star Trek: The Motion Picture is a science fiction,
adventure, mystery film directed by Robert Wise.
When an unidentified alien destroys three powerful
Klingon cruisers, Captain James T.
Kirk returns to the newly transformed U.S.S.
Enterprise to take command.
Admiral James T. Kirk, played by William Shatner.
Mr. Spock, played by Leonard Nimoy.
Dr. Leonard 'Bones' McCoy, played by DeForest Kelley.
Cmdr. Montgomery 'Scotty' Scott, played by James Doohan.
Lt. Cmdr. Hikaru Sulu, played by George Takei.
Lt. Pavel Chekov, played by Walter Koenig.
Star Trek: The Motion Picture is a 1979 American science
fiction film directed by Robert Wise.
The Motion Picture is based on and stars the cast of the 1966–1969 television
series Star Trek created by Gene Roddenberry, who serves as producer.
In the film, set in the 2270s, a mysterious and powerful alien cloud known as
V'Ger approaches Earth, destroying everything in its path.
Admiral James T.
Kirk (William Shatner) assumes command of the recently refitted Starship Enterprise to
lead it on a mission to determine V'Ger's origins and save the planet.
When Star Trek was cancelled in 1969, Roddenberry lobbied Paramount
Pictures to continue the franchise through a feature film.
The success of the series in syndication convinced the
studio to begin work on the film in 1975.
A series of writers and scripts did not satisfy
Paramount, and they scrapped the film project.
Instead, Paramount planned on returning the franchise to its roots,
with a new television series titled Star Trek: Phase II.
The box office success of Star Wars and Close Encounters of the Third Kind convinced Paramount
to change course, cancelling production of Phase II and resuming work on a film.
In March 1978, Paramount announced Wise would direct a $15 million
film adaptation of the original television series.
Filming began that August and concluded the following January.
With the cancellation of Phase II, writers rushed to adapt its
planned pilot episode, "In Thy Image", into a film script.
Constant revisions to the story and the shooting script continued to
the extent of hourly script updates on shooting dates.
The Enterprise was modified inside and out, costume designer Robert Fletcher provided new
uniforms, and production designer Harold Michelson fabricated new sets.
Jerry Goldsmith composed the film's score, beginning an
association with Star Trek that would continue until 2002.
When the original contractors for the optical effects proved unable to complete their tasks in time,
effects supervisor Douglas Trumbull was asked to meet the film's December 1979 release date.
Wise took the just-completed film to its Washington, D.C., opening, but always felt that
the final theatrical version was a rough cut of the film he wanted to make.
Released in North America on December 7, 1979, Star Trek: The Motion Picture received mixed reviews,
many of which faulted it for a lack of action scenes and over-reliance on special effects.
Its final production cost ballooned to approximately $44 million, and it earned $139 million worldwide,
short of studio expectations but enough for Paramount to propose a less expensive sequel.
Roddenberry was forced out of creative control for the
sequel, Star Trek II: The Wrath of Khan (1982).
In 2001, Wise oversaw a director's cut for a special DVD release of the film, with
remastered audio, tightened and added scenes, and new computer-generated effects.
The film explores themes of spacecraft, man vs machine, artificial
intelligence (a.i.), self sacrifice, teleportation.
The tone is lighthearted and thought_provoking and mind_bending.